Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Victor Gutierrez Papers, 1970-1987
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Victor Gutierrez papers 1970-1987
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
2.5 linear feet Extent: 1875 Items
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the largest and oldest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Victor Gutierrez served as Executive Vice President of the Finance division, and as Chief Financial Officer, at JWT. The Victor Gutierrez Papers cover the years 1970-1987, with the bulk of materials dating from the 1980s. The collection primarily consists of employee manuals, company policy information, marketing plans, operations reviews and financial reports relating to JWT domestic and international offices. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
RL.00706
Language: Material in English, Turkish
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Victor Gutierrez Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1993.
Biographical Note
Victor Gutierrez received a B.S. in Business Administration and Accounting from St. Peter's College in New Jersey. He worked at J. Walter Thompson (JWT) during the 1970s and 80s. In 1976, he was elected Executive Vice President of the Finance division, and in 1986, he became Chief Financial Officer. During a hostile take-over attempt at JWT in 1987, Gutierrez resigned and was replaced by Terence Martin.
Following his tenure at JWT, Gutierrez owned several fast food franchises and private retail outlets before joining the staff of Young & Rubicam. There, he served in various capacities for the Latin American division, including as Vice President of Business Affairs, Worldwide Financial Director for the Colgate-Palmolive account, and as Vice Chairman. He eventually managed over 23 advertising agencies across Latin America. In 1999, Gutierrez began working as Senior Vice President for Yupi Internet, Inc., a family-owned business in Miami, Florida.
Collection Overview
The Victor Gutierrez Papers cover the years 1970-1987, with the bulk of materials dating from the 1980s. The collection primarily consists of employee manuals, company policy information, marketing plans, operations reviews and financial reports relating to JWT domestic and international offices.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: the Domestic Offices Series and the International Offices Series. The Domestic Offices Series contains employee manuals, information on company policies, marketing plans, operations reviews and financial reports. Also includes memoranda and reports related to the Operations Management Group (OMG) and Thompson Recruitment Advertising (TRA), including audits. The International Offices Series contains primarily office agreements and reports related to the business, including financial gains and losses, of JWT international offices.
Subject Headings
Gutierrez, Victor, 1945-; J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company -- History; Advertising agencies -- Management; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives include:
New York Office Records
Don Johnston Papers
Frankfurt Office. Denis Lanigan Papers
Bertram Metter Papers
Jack Peters Papers
Thomas Sutton Papers
Contents of Collection
- Domestic Offices Series, 1970-1987, (5 boxes)
  Series contains employee manuals, information on company policies, marketing plans, operations reviews and financial reports. Also includes memoranda and reports related to the Operations Management Group (OMG) and Thompson Recruitment Advertising (TRA), including audits. Original folder titles were maintained and items were arranged alphabetically.
  - Accounting Manual, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Annotated Financials, Annual Report, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Broadcast Traffic Documentation, 1983 Mar., (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Client Compensation Handbook, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Client Compensation Handbook, Executive Summary, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Finance Manual, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - History Income Statements, 1976-1985, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - JWT Management Development Center, Employee Selection Interviewing Techniques, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Labor Relations-U.S. Media, 1983 Mar., (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Mailroom Operation Documentation, 1982 Apr. (Box 2)
  - Marketing Committee, 1984-1985, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Marketing Plan, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - Monthly Managers Assessments, 1986-1987, (1-3 of 4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Monthly Managers Assessments, 1986-1987 (continued), (4 of 4 folders) (Box 3)
  - O'Donnell Board Meeting Presentation, 1986 May (Box 3)
  - Operation Management Group meetings, 1986, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Operating Policies, 1981-1986 (Box 3)
  - Operational Review, 1986 May 14, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Operations Review of Selected Accounting ahd Administrative Areas, 1985 Aug. (Box 4)
  - Press-Outside Reports, 1970-1972, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Regional Financial Directors
    - Meeting, 1986 Feb. (Box 4)
    - Responsibilities, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Securities Exchange Commission Annual Reports, 1984-1986, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Spot Bill/Pay Documentation, 1983 Jan., (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Spot Processing Documentation, 1982 June, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Spot Processing Documentation, 1982 June(continued), (2 of 2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Stock Review and Commentary, 1985 Mar. 31 (Box 5)
  - Strategic Plan, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Thompson Company-Twelve Months Results, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Thompson Recruitment Advertising
    - General files, 1984-1986, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Internal Audit Report, 1985 Dec. 2 (Box 5)
    - Management Incentive Plan, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Operational Reviews, 1984-1986, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Planning, 1986 Aug. 11 (Box 5)
- International Offices Series, 1982-1986, (2 boxes)
  Contains primarily office agreements and reports related to the business, including financial gains and losses, of JWT international offices. Also includes files related to trips made to international offices by Gutierrez. Original folder titles were maintained and items were arranged alphabetically.
  - Europe, General, Financial, 1986 (Box 5)
  - European Management Group minutes, 1986 Sept. (Box 5)
  - Greece, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Hindustan Thompson Associates, Ltd., Annual Report, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - International Services Documentation, 1982 July (Box 6)
  - JWT International, Gains and Losses, 1982-1985, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Mexican Relief Fund, 1985-1986 (Box 6)
  - South Africa, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Spain, 1983 (Box 6)
    [Includes presentation by M. Elexpuru: Plan for a New Structure, 1983 Dec. 9.]
  - Turkey, 1986 (Box 6)